foreign
[Music]
welcome to active live stream number
50.0
it is October 17 2022 and we are
starting the series on interoception as
modeling allostasis as control
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following good video
etiquette for live streams
today in 50.0 we're starting this series
discussing the paper interception as
modeling allostasis as control
the authors are Eli synesh Jordan
therialt Dana Brooks John wilheim Von
DeMint Lisa Feldman Barrett and Karen s
Quigley
it is a paper published in the journal
biological psychology in January of 2022
and this is just an introduction and
context video as Dean here and I
work through this paper and discuss some
related topics
we're going to go over some big
questions basic aims and Abstract
roadmap of the paper then go into the
paper touch on a few key points and
images and themes and then primarily
look forward to discussing it with any
authors or anyone else who'd like to
join in the coming weeks
all right so I'm Daniel I'm a researcher
in California and
the paper was selected by decentralized
upvote
it was uh fun to read and it brings some
new topics into our regime of attention
so I'm looking forward to this and I'll
pass to Dean
thanks Charlie I'm Dean I'm here in
Calgary
I think what's interesting about any
paper that um pulls to seemingly
discreet
things and put some proximal and gets
them entangling and then pulls them
apart again and tries to look at sort of
what happens when things get combined is
always something that I'm always
interested in that in fact it was the
title of this and the fact that they
were bringing allostasis and
teresception together and what what does
that mean was the reason why I spent a
little bit of time on this and really
I'm quite interested in hearing what the
authors have to say now that they put
this idea to
to work
right how would you describe the big
question
well I mean I think the focus here is on
on what happens and what we can say
about controller requirements necessary
to carry out physiological tasks varying
degrees of complexity
um
I've never been really sure how the the
specificity of different outcomes and
behaviors looks in aggregate but I think
one of the things that we can say is if
there is a predictive component and
there's a feedback component
and they're focusing on two particular
types of that
um it's interesting perhaps what kind of
generalities we can walk away with
um never you know sort of not getting
lost in the weeds of well this happened
here and then that happened there but
just on that General level what what
sorts of things when those two things
are put together
um should we say as a certain pattern or
commonality
nice I agree I would put it in the
category of asking how a given system
independent
or modality independent phenomena like
allostasis which is anticipatory changes
in physiology and connects with a domain
or a use case like interception and it
does seem like a lot of the models that
we've explored have been visual or
conceptual or symbolic
and the interceptive modality has popped
up again and again in discussions and so
this is a cool opportunity to look at
some formalisms for interception
okay here's the paper
as described earlier just a few of the
highlights that were written by the
authors on the
publication page
interception enables the brain to
anticipate the body's upcoming metabolic
needs interception provides performance
metrics for viscera motor regulation
we connect control theory with decision
making and motor control of the body
we model allostatic control as optimal
control with the time varying reference
signal
they talk about some
limitations of previous models and some
unique aspects of what their model does
and the way that they formulate the apic
model
anything to add
no I think their aims are
straightforward
okay on claim so Dean and I were
looking into
thinking of ourselves
in terms of claims adjusters appraisers
examiners and investigators
as we
pulled out a whole handful of really
important and salient
within the argument of this relatively
long
and technically scaffolded paper
and pulling out a bunch of claims that
are written that connect the dots and
set some of the relevant uh
interpretations for the formalisms
do you want to highlight any of them or
it's fine to just have them
for anyone who wants to yeah
off of this but I will say this here
there is a I think a parallel trying to
be drawn here between
predictive
predictive uh processing no I'm not
saying that predictive processing but
processing as a as a predictive device
and feelings
and control and feedback and so I think
there are a lot of claims that can be
made
but that's a really really
um nuanced and also a very very
complex
uh space to play in and so I can
understand why
um there's lots and lots of claims
um again whether or not or how far those
claims can hold before they break down
will be an interesting thing to talk to
with the authors
yeah well said it's a very intertwined
area maybe that's what you're pointing
towards when you say complex operating
yeah I have a lot of hair so it's It's
Tricky for me
all right
abstract
okay I'll read the first three
the brain regulates the body by
anticipating its needs and attempting to
meet them before they arise a process
called allostasis
allostasis requires a model of the
changing sensory conditions within the
body a process called interception in
this paper we examine how interoception
may provide performance feedback for
allostasis
we suggest studying allostasis in terms
of control theory reviewing control
theories applications to related issues
in physiology motor control and decision
making
we synthesize these by relating them to
the important properties of outostatic
Regulation as a control problem we then
sketch a normal formalism for how the
brain might perform allostatic control
of the viscera by analogy two skeletal
motor control including a mathematical
View and how intersection acts as a
performance feedback for allostasis
finally we suggest ways to test
implications of our hypothesis
okay onto the roadmap
paper starts with introduction to
function
of the brain in the body
and then introduces some of the key
pillars or foundations of their
synthesis and interpretation
which is interception
control theory as an approach for
unifying physiology motor control
decision making
and allostasis as a trajectory
tracking stochastic optimal control
the fifth section is a discussion and
then there's an appendix B and C
and in their words four sections in this
paper connect interception to allostasis
section two establishes how
interoception enables the brain to
estimate the physiological efficiency of
the body in the present moment which is
precisely what it needs to know to
evaluate and refine action
Section 3 introduces control theory
section 4 applies the principles of
control theory to derive a novel format
model of how the brain might estimate
the desirability of physiological
trajectories and make prospective
regulatory decisions finally Section 5
synthesizes the previous three sections
to explore the direct implications of
the proposed formalism appendix a
provides a glossary of terms but this is
moved up and it's no longer an appendix
so there's no appendix a
appendix B1 provides mathematical
details related to section 3 and
appendix C1 provides mathematical
details related to section 4.
the keywords were interception
allostasis and predictive processing
we're going to talk a lot about
interception and allostasis
somewhat in this dot zero but certainly
in the coming discussions and for
predictive processing a good recent
stream is live stream number 43 with
Maria
okay also just for reference we'll pause
on these just long enough for you to
screenshot them if you want
there's a nomenclature table
with the definition of many words so
here's the first nomenclature terms 1
through 25.
and then here's the second half of the
nomenclature 26 to 49.
sort it alphabetically
anything to add on the nomenclature
other than to say that
it's good that they provided it and
it'll be used in the coming sections
well I think it's interesting that you
pointed out that the um they pulled they
pulled the definitions forward and then
when you look at the formalisms and so I
think from the standpoint of what they
what they want to message around
this
this braiding
um requires us to at least get a
Common Sense around what things mean
before we start
trying to pull apart what they equal
so yeah I kind of what kind of like that
well said
all right section one introduction the
functions of the brain in the body
okay
there's an evocative beginning to this
paper
um playing a simple game of dodgeball
then requires your brain to continually
coordinate the systems of your body
and this motif of dodgeball is going to
be
returning again
and on the left is a hugging face
implementation of a stable diffusion
algorithm The Prompt of the image was
DodgeBall playful ants active inference
free energy principle
and while we were making the slides we
were engaged in active inference with
some of these image generating
affordances and allowing that to
do what
well I think it's really interesting
that this what what the generator said
this would be the result of a
coordinated
um
what's the word I'm looking for
entanglement of these of these prompts
but didn't talk anything about what what
strategy each one of those
um Silhouettes is now employing
and I think that there is an implied
sense that there's a strategy going on
as well so again when you bring some of
these really interesting things together
um it I guess it depends on how deep you
want to go how much you want to
dimensionalize the space
so what is that right there yeah this is
the same prompt this was just another
one this one's coming more a little more
photorealistic
a little bit more like
elusive you know are they playing
dodgeball
yeah
are they just inferring
all right next keyword you can go for it
if you just people can read the
definition here but just give your own
take what is interception
well I think at the at the end of the
day there's there's a certain amount of
signaling signaling going on that we
become aware of sometimes young people
or all people like sort of categorize
them all under the umbrella of feelings
and uh
I grabbed this from tots On Target just
because I always worked in that kind of
space of how do we keep this as simple
as we can and so when you get these
signals these sensory signals originate
from within the body these are the
feelings you get and uh whether or not
you connect them to the world outside of
your
skin or your margins
um sometimes you do sometimes you don't
you just wake up with a tummy ache right
so what does that mean about today
nice
I would say a little narrowly
interception is referring to some
observation and inference on hidden
States
with a referent that's in Tarot inside
of the body as opposed to X tarot
outside the body but there's probably
also a lot of like blurring and what is
the retina really doing is it doing
inference on itself and where is it
actually doing inference on the outside
world
structure all right interceptive
internal models you added some images so
what are they
so I'll just read this real quick so
psychologists refer to the internal mod
including interception by many terms and
I think it I think that's important
because there hasn't always been
agreement about clearly defining what an
internal model is
um things like unconscious interest
seems to fit into this umbrella embodied
simulation Concepts and categories
controlled hallucination which was new
to me because I don't know what that
even means uh and regardless of what
it's called the brain is hypothesized to
construct a dynamic model of its body in
the world in this paper we use the terms
prediction simulation and concept and so
to somebody with sort of my deep
research background in terms of
abduction the the signal the interpreted
the object
um what is that model how do we how do
we avoid getting into another great
debate about whether that's
representational and content filled or
not or is there something that
we
sense From the Inside every every every
single time data is coming at us and
being poured
onto our different sensory surfaces
exterior exterior on the outside
I I think that there's a piece that
comes from the outside I know when the
temperature goes up in the room but my
temperature might also be going up
because I ate a bad shrimp and it's
sometimes difficult to figure out
whether or not it's because the heat
gone up or whether my body's responding
with an inflammatory
gesture
yeah that's a
nice Point like sometimes called a
difference making cause or difference
that makes a difference does a viral
infection cause the body temperature to
rise
and or to what extent can that be
decomposed into factors from the virus
versus this the Dynamics changing of the
immune system
so
interesting image on the left knows I
can't tell whether the image on the left
by the image on the left what's what
speed the image on the right is actually
moving down the road and that's kind of
why I wanted the ambiguity there
for an enteroceptor model because you
know demacio talks a lot about what what
can we really
describe and pursue precise terms and
what remains somewhat ambiguous and the
authors in this paper talk a little bit
about God as well yeah when the referent
is external it's objective then there's
the opportunity for multiple external
perspectives to align not even saying
that's better but just the opportunity
to whereas if the embodied behavior of
your physiological set point for some
physiological regulation
is changed it doesn't have the same
opportunity for external alignment again
for better and For Worse
and almost always with difficulty
communicating or sometimes measuring in
laboratory settings as well and quote
controlling
So speaking with authors on this and why
they study this modality
will be interesting all right as for the
computational or
system independent phenomena that
they're going to be trying to integrate
with Alice with in tersection is
allostasis they Define this term as
allostasis is to anticipate changing
needs evaluate priorities and prepare
the organism to satisfy them before they
lead to errors a process called
allostasis so let's just say that you
have an allostatic model of the
temperature in the room
and the core body temperature doesn't
change so then can one look back and say
it didn't change because it was expected
to change
and somebody will just say well how do
you know it worked then because it
didn't raise the body temperature
I focused on the part that the fact that
they describe it as a three-part process
so me being always talking about what's
the minimum here what's the minimum here
we need in order to be able to to do
this I find that really not really quite
interesting
why three
not four or five are breaking it out
into into smaller slices that's again
another one of those questions I'd like
to be able to talk to the authors about
all right active inference
they wrote
before
diving into formal modeling details
below which we're going to get to later
in the paper
it might be helpful to compare and
contrast the approach here
apic
with the prominent modeling framework
active inference and we're going to
return to some of these details and I'm
sure have a lot of discussion on it but
you made a really interesting point in
our preparation about how they're not
treating their model as
Downstream or a corollary of any
commitment to a particular physics which
is how we often hear about free energy
principle basically mechanics
but rather they're treating
the
model as a first order construction
anything you want to add on that because
I thought that was really like help me
frame what the paper was about
yeah that's Street part I think that the
work bullet unlike most active interest
models in the literature are the
material below considers an indefinite
time or infinite Horizon control setting
is interesting because that makes it
really really clear between what they're
talking about and what we often see in a
lot of the representations which is t0
T1 to T
whatever
in terms of being able to figure out
what is going on sequentially so
all right cool
this section in the introduction talks
about some issues with other models
they talk about how existing models of
interception have either formulated
allostasis as a prospective
decision-making problem
without considering how these decisions
are enacted which has a bunch of
different interpretations but maybe for
example requiring the enumeration of
policies and then the selection from
policies
or as a motor control problem without
considering where motor commands come
from
another issue they have with other
models rather than treat metabolic
efficiency as the objective they discuss
homeostasis the regulation of bodily
variables to fix set points with fixed
tolerance for error
so this is really going to be a cool
theme which is
rather than fix the set point and
variability
see that outcome as being due to some
other process that does result in an
attracting set or point with a fixed set
point and an empirical tolerance for
error as well as maybe some points of no
return and so on
but seeing all those outcomes as the
realization of a dynamical system that
actually doesn't pursue a set point but
rather pursues a slope on a graph that
we'll explore and that like zone of
maximum controllability
and reduction of surprisal around the
zone of maximum controllability
over evolutionary time will come to be
associated with this kind of a survival
variable
and some other points okay anything else
well it's relationship relationship
relationship and then they say this
paper aims to fill this Gap
I think in relationship doesn't
necessarily imply that things have to
get
closed in terms of whatever the Gap is
by filling something in I think I think
the fact that they talk about targeting
I think about the fact that they see
relationship as playing
kind of the key role in what they think
is happening here
um means that that they maybe the gap
um continues I mean they're they're
putting stuff in here for us to consider
and contemplate but I'm not sure
if we're actually filling a gap where
we're just sort of understanding what's
in this space
right
section two so at the beginning of
section two the top
paragraphs interception modeling the
body estimating its efficiency and then
the below the fold
section 2.5 the summary so both of these
pre and post 2.
um 2.0
2.2
contains a lot of structural information
about the key points in this paper
anything to add on this specific slide
to or we'll just go into the sections
star down at the very bottom there
people might want to have a read on that
because I think that's and that's saying
that that's controversial but I do think
is interesting yeah
um that the the movement towards the
responsive range of a capacity curve
could be potentially obviating the need
for a dedicated neural circuit or module
that specifically calculates the
behavioral constructs of rewarding costs
so what is it
mean to move into uh
non-reward-centric
understanding of physiology
or reinterpreting reward
okay section 2.1 introduces a
distinction that is going to be key in
the rest of the paper which is the
difference between two types of visceral
sensory variables interceptive
those which represent quantities of
resources regulated resources and those
which represents rates at which
processes act controlled processes
regulated resources are kept stable
relatively stable over time examples
include blood glucose and core body
temperature
so of note is they don't have to be a
depletable resource
the regulated resource is kind of like
the bounded variable in a physiology in
a homeostasis context it's not
necessarily A depletable like metabolite
uh regulated resource like blood glucose
or core body temperature represents a
physical quantity or a substance like
glucose its quantity cannot change
instantaneously so I think it will be
interesting to ask like
what different uh regulated resources
of different modalities are
and then controlled processes
are the rates at which physiological
processes operate so in that case would
be like the kind of input output
relationships of blood glucose
okay yeah we just talk about that we
talked about that recently is what's the
difference between gripper and gript and
can both exist at once
nice
2.2 back to the DodgeBall example the
heart rate and the blood pressure must
increase during aerobic exercise as
noted in the DodgeBall example
so there has to be some physiological
adaptation
in order to start exercising and
continue exercising
upon resting conditions the baroreceptor
that's pressure receptor heart rate
reflex would normally counter any rise
in blood pressure by slowing the
heartbeat however with exertion your
blood pressure and heart rate both must
increase to support the needed increase
in blood flow required by your
exercising muscles
and so then there's a discussion of how
this kind of modulation of reflex allows
for uh shifting of an entire function
relating a change in blood pressure to a
change in your heart rate
so this is describing like a dynamical
systems approach and physiological model
for how the causal or correlational
structure of different physiological
variables can be modeled
pretty generally but it's going to get
more specific
yeah a little bit of covariation there
and uh
and Physiology and away we go
okay 2.2 predicting and modeling the
ranges of regulated and controlled
processes this is describing some of the
parameters
of
the Curve
the threshold and saturation points
which partly derive Define curves that
are derived from functions
which physiologists commonly use to
model the connection between
perturbations and Regulatory responses
usually naming them response curves or
transfer functions
and then the term capacity curves will
be used to emphasize the fact that while
such curves can shift over time
in any one instant they represent the
current range of limited regulatory
resources available to an organism
so one could imagine like a financial
capacity curve to maintain some
Market at some point like kind of like
the depth
but by
analogy
and then this um
idea of modeling how a system responds
to perturbations
doesn't necessarily require modeling the
internal model of that system but as you
build a better generative model of the
system being perturbed than the better
experiments and the further you can uh
have kind of perturbability of the
system it allows you to approach your
system without a strong hypothesis about
its structure
the capacity curve in figure two point
or in figure one has the mathematical
form and then figure one is shown
alongside with equation one
the parameters are defined the function
y is uh taking in U mu K being R Big B
and combining those into an equation
the figure one on the x-axis is showing
the blood pressure
and then the y-axis is showing the
Baseline activation percentage of the
reflex modulating this physiological
variable so at 100 which is the target
blood pressure or sort of what would be
called the homeostatic set point because
it seems to be an attractor
at that point the Baseline activation of
the barrel reflex is happening
when the blood pressure increases then
the barrel reflex activates up to 2x
thresholding at 2x activation of
Baseline and then as the blood pressure
decreases the barrel reflex again with
this sigmoid symmetry decreases
that's a dynamical model of regulation
of blood pressure
equations 2 3 and 4.
outline the form of a generative model a
procedure for probabilistically
predicting observed variables in terms
of unobserved variables
the variables listed are unobserved
variables which are sampled from an A
Priory probability distribution not
dependent on data
so that's referring to using a
generative model and how these equations
constitute it
The Proposal here has an unusual feature
the equations for X the mean arterial
blood pressure and why the barrel reflex
activation as a percentage of Baseline
so figure 1 X and Y
or in terms of the quantile variable U
the quantile variable uniformly
represents the relationship between the
blood pressure and the barrel reflex
activation irrespective of changes in
the capacity curve's operating Point mu
and gain K the quantile depends only on
the functional form of the capacity
curve and not on the parameters so we'll
unpack that a little more technically
but they point to that as a feature of
their model
here again is figure one a little bigger
with more space to discuss later and
here's figure two
which is the capacity curve from figure
one in blue with a linearized response
in Orange
around the operating point the Blue
Diamond marker
so
one can see this as the maximum positive
slope of this sigmoid curve
and that under
the specification
that the reflex is going to be activated
in a sigmoidal way
then depending on whether one is in like
a curving up part or a curving down part
or thinks about it as pursuing the
maximum positive slope
then pursuing that point and being
rewarded by movements towards maximum
maneuverability and control
would have the equivalent of pursuing a
homeostatic model where this is like a
fixed Point attractor
so it puts the kind of bottom of the
bowl
in this Orange Line being maximized in
slope rather than the Blue Diamond being
reduced in its distance from 100.
right
I think we copied this
section twice
it was so unusual we copied it twice
yeah 2.3
return to the DodgeBall example
and they're going to widen their scope
Beyond just the Barrow reflex blood
pressure
to circulating levels of oxygen glucose
and carbon dioxide
next we focus on blood glucose as a
regulated resource with glucagon as the
controlled process enabling secretion of
glucose into the blood and Insulin as
the Control process enabling removal of
glucose from the blood so the barrel
reflex was like a single volume knob
or a triage nurse that can lower or
raise the single response so if some
physiological variable is high it's like
it can be like removed
glucose regulation has multiple hormones
it's going to be like buffered from two
different sides in a slightly different
way but using a lot of the same
formalisms and logic
to introduce a slightly
different and more complex physiological
system
okay
um the section discusses some findings
that blood blood glucose levels are not
actively defended at a biologically
hard-coded set point any more than heart
rate is instead glucagon and Insulin two
hormones
activity balance each other's effects to
bring the blood glucose to a point
within its settling range
with glucose entering the blood after
the person ingests food and glucose then
Crossing from the blood into other
bodily tissues to support their function
anything to add on this
slide not not specifically now wait till
we get to the end of section the second
two stuff
so here is figure three
they're writing figure three
shows plots of the resulting functions
of this equation
applied to the insulin case
which can be interpreted as capacity
curves orange sigmoid is insulin
the blue sigmoid is glucagon
they have different hormone levels at
different x-axis which is the level of
glucose in the blood and so you kind of
see familiar behavior when glucose is
high then insulin is at high secretion
which drives the absorption of glucose
and when glucose gets low in this case
below 2.5 or 3 or so then
glucagon is secreted to elicit glucose
to enter the blood
okay
and so one can imagine that the glucose
level will be oscillating in this space
but not exactly
set
at a set point with a residual being
minimized
section 2.4
is where they move from discussing this
kind of a regulatory model
uh into viable ranges and capacities
could obviate a modular reward system
here's an argument or appeal to
neuroanatomy there's no single brain
site that specifically encodes
appetitive or aversive reinforcement
value it is useful to reframe discrete
reward and decision systems as domain
General allostatic control systems
the domain generality of interception
provides further theoretical support for
the idea that we do not need mental
modules or faculty psychology Concepts
to understand how a brain works
a mathematically sound and biologically
plausible account of allostatic control
does not require a modular or separate
reward system in the central nervous
system
and a bit more on this topic anything to
add
now let's get to 37.
all right the rewards of control so here
I wanted to highlight two papers with
some nice images
by both papers involving Tobias Norville
and these papers are cited in the paper
under discussion and they all show some
pretty interesting features so just to
highlight some of these
graphs here's movements within a glucose
and temperature space so regulation of
multiple physiological variables
here on the bottom left is the
integration of interception homeostatic
set point and motor commands like
related to foraging
here is some Bayesian
visualizations with a prior posterior
unlikelihood and about this two-way
relationship of inference and a former
dynamical model the tale of two
densities and then last one this is uh
another body temperature glucose
modeling approach
that
that gets to that notion that we
describe as going to the bottom of the
bowl
where the shape of this
napkin
could be designed or evolved or selected
so that the marble spends most of its
time in a certain Zone and this is like
just one other way to think about
these types of attractor systems
rather than as like traces or so on
okay anything to add
well I think section two basically
confirms that if you're going to be
doing any kind of predictive performance
that has a an element of continuity to
it that depends on on sort of
recognizable finite limits and also
variability within whatever those limits
are
and I think that um
kind of speaks to the idea that there's
in a in a sort of a two-factor situation
there's signaling that looks like this
and they sort of pointed out a couple of
examples of the barrel reflex and the
and the glucagon thing and
they also were trying to avoid
oversimplifying or over reducing like
they they tried to keep
the complexity of those two examples
retained in terms of what they were
trying to hold up is is something that
allows us to start looking at these
capacity curves
all right section three control theory
the unifying lens for physiology motor
control and decision making
and then one of their summaries of the
chapter this section
introduces Concepts from engineering
control theory then reviews its
applications in the Life Sciences these
include physiology section 3.1 skeletal
motor movement section 3.2 and decision
making section 3.3 section 3.4 will
connect future interceptive states to
present movements Illuminating what
makes allostatic regulation more energy
efficient than homeostatic regulation
the next section 4 will build off the
account of control used in physiology to
suggest how interception supports
allostasis
okay here we're not going to read
everything on the slide but this is from
section 3.1 control theory for
physiology a reliable a reliable body
built from unreliable Parts anything to
add on this
nope
people just want to read this yep I'll
just call out for a controller to
perform well it must contain some sort
of copy or mirror of the plant's
expected Behavior which is referred to
as an internal model
control theorists called assist the
driven system to plant and its desired
trajectory the reference trajectory
and there's some interesting discussion
of this kind of um
thread of control theory
figure four
so figure four is a functional block
diagram of model based control system
the plant in Orange is the object or
system whose motion or other behavior is
controlled
the controller purple sends signals
controls solid block arrows
the change how the plant moves and
signals the expected outcome predictions
solid yellow arrow to the state
estimator in yellow and so on people can
read the rest of it
for these figures Daniel as we get
further down in the slides why don't I
read and then you can run the cursor
over the different parts of the model so
people can kind of see and can real time
with how the two things align sounds
good we'll do that for the future ones
and this is gonna
revoke or uh recall
that of our earlier discussions in live
stream 23 skillful performance and
interactionism and instructionism and
how to think about motor plants and so
on right
section 3.2 moving the body the
reference control hypothesis so the
reference control hypothesis the
citations provided were to Feldman 2015
and latash 2021
and the reference control hypothesis
describes the skeletal motor system in
terms of a hierarchy of controllers with
higher level controllers in the brain
prescribing reference trajectories to
the lower level reflexes in the spinal
cord these reflexes then compare the
actual length of the muscle as signaled
by afferent proprioceptor neurons to the
reference length sent down by the brain
and contracts the muscle to bring the
two into agreement and so here is the
top part of the table of content of
Feldman's 2015 book referent control of
action and perception and the paper of
latash in physics of Life review 2021
with some graphics around this type of
approach
foreign
you can start with this slide on the
real world
okay well I'll just point out a couple
things the authors say because they they
do not want to be accused of sort of
overfitting here
start your motor control experiment is
only limited overlap with the actual
structure of motor control so
only limited overlap experiment on
reaching behaviors involves an
experimenter prescribing the reaching
task to the participants participants
brain does not function specifically to
follow instructions from an experimenter
but rather to regulate their own body
the actual organization of the central
nervous system occurs better with an
inside out view of motor function
movement of the body I.E the somatous
somatomotor pathways surge regulation of
the Body for example in the game with Dr
value if you unexpectedly step on a hard
or sharp block or object you usually
don't purposely impale yourself who have
stepped on it so I just wanted to go
through my foot now
because I might my focus is still on
stabilizing my posture gravity with coil
and pain you feel that interceptively
and the unplanned disturbance of any
tissue damage requires you to make a
decision about what to do next excuse
yourself to nurse your foot or play
through that pain
I think the fact that they're trying to
limit what they are saying is the extent
to which the goal piece of this
can be said to apply as a good thing
because I think there's a couple of
areas
around
so what is in this relationship between
a command system or a control system and
a demand system where do things like
like when your body is
started to suffer from mild hypothermia
and and you know people know that that
your brain stops functioning correctly
um how do you differentiate between for
example
um I'm getting a Slurpee headache and
you put the Slurpee down and stop
drinking it because you know that that's
the effect versus you have your limbs
which aren't you know frostbitten at
this point or at least hopefully not for
us button continue to move so that you
don't stop you you you avoid stopping
moving all together which is which
essentially is death so here we've got a
wonder whether or not
um without getting into the argument of
because it's pretty obvious if your
brain is dead you're dead but if your
hands are dead or and you are still
alive that clear distinction between a
command center consequence and a demand
Center consequence what does that mean
in terms of okay so there's things that
happen that you do automatically in
order to keep yourself alive in some of
the most critical situations and it's
not like yours your your
your hand has the brain and yet it may
in just simply moving around Beyond a
reflexive thing be able to keep you
alive long enough until somebody comes
to your rescue as a as a for example
so I don't know if that's confusing or
not but I think that there's a
reconciliation but that goes on between
command and demand and maybe some of
control is the ability to give up
commanded times in order for a new
a new response to take over and keep you
alive and you may not necessarily
um know how to do that from a command
center so we'll have to talk to the
authors about that because these are
questions that I have because I got a
bit of a physiological background so I
wonder about these extreme situations
all right
section 33 making decisions constructing
future reference trajectories
they use the word demands so
we'll talk about it later yep more
quotes from three three for those who
want to screenshot
talking about ergonicity which is also
raised in the appendix B which we're not
going to focus on
okay you can read figure five and I'll
use the mouse uh so a functional block
diagram for an experiment experimental
psychologist task oriented view of motor
control the diagram shows a formal logic
structure here
at a conceptual level the boxes and
arrows do not map onto the anatomy of
the brain or nervous system in contrast
to figure four the diagram
differentiates between skeletal motor
brain
and peripheral stretch reflex
controllers and between sensory State
estimators brain and peripheral sense
organs sensory surfaces sensory surfaces
the diagram shows an engineering
perspective
important to note that on a psychology
experiment in which the experimenter
prescribes a task for Behavior to
participants so there's an externality
and a participant's brain then acts as a
control system to achieve the behavior
the prescribed Behavior
systems that maintain the body therefore
serve systems that move the body
which in turn serve a prescribed
Behavior so again focus on the
prescriptive the externality the
information coming in
all right
function of laptop yeah next one
functional block diagram for a control
theoretic view of allostasis in contrast
to figure five this diagram shows a
closed loop control system designed for
autonomous regulation of the body and
experimenter's desired task behaviors
replaced with or by sorry the allostatic
capacity estimator
which sends predictions of capacity
curves which we've already looked at to
the interior receptive State estimator
and receives prediction errors with
which to update its estimates
the updated estimates are issued as a
reference signal to the visitor motor
controller this diagram shows a formal
logical structure a conceptual level the
hypothesis depicted is constrained by
the inferred anatomical structures in
Bear 2017 but the boxes and arrows do
not map
a repeat do not map one to one onto the
anatomy of the brain or nervous system
all right
great
so just to highlight the difference here
the left is almost like an
instructionalist
Arrangements and this is how the
experimental psychologist thinks about
this task which is like we write down
the instructions the pseudocode for the
task keep your heart rate within this
range
and then there's some decision making
with the Skeletor motor system whether
capable of conscious action
and stretching
or more uh subconscious
and then acting through physiology in
the body or in the external world that
interceptive state estimator comes into
alignment with the desired
implementation of the skeletal motor
decision
in contrast the role of the task
instructions so to speak is substituted
in this control theoretic View
with the allostatic capacity estimator
as the imperative and that feeds on
through a very similar set on the right
side but here we actually have the
viscera motor decision controller
in uh in contrast to a scalar motor
decision controller because this is more
focused on like
choose the left button or the right
button and figure six is focused more on
the kind of barrel reflex
control theory view but that also
generalizes Beyond
okay I think that's just another view
section four allostasis as trajectory
tracking stochastic optimal control
this section will describe our formal
model of allostatic decision making the
allostatic path integral control apic
model
apic has a simple idea at its core just
as perceptual Concepts serve as internal
models of the body's sensory surfaces
action Concepts also serve as internal
models of potential behaviors and their
predicted outcomes
section 4.1 drives an SOC
objective function from the mathematical
form by which section 2 represented
capacity curves
then section 4.2 4.3 and 4.4 are
described flushing out this apic model
anything to add
no let's go there all right 4.1
transforming capacity curves into
objective functions
since any given capacity curve such as
the 1 and figure 1 above
which is a maximum value on the vertical
axis it can be divided by its maximum y
value to normalize it to range between 0
and 1. once normalized in this way it
can be interpreted as a cumulative
distribution function from probability
Theory
this is precisely in fact precisely what
srinivasan Laughlin and dubs
did to interpret the firing of retinal
neurons and flies as a form of
predictive coding see there figure one
the derivative of a CDF cumulative
distribution function yields a
probability density function PDF
so the derivative of a CDF gives a PDF
this is the more familiar way of
representing a probability distribution
where the height on the vertical axis
corresponds to likelihood in the PDF
but for a PDF derived from a capacity
curve it represents relative
responsiveness to perturbation we will
call such distribution a reference
distribution
so this is a transformation of
statistical distributions between the
PDF which is the probability density
function and CDF cumulative distribution
function
it might be very familiar to some it
might be totally new to some so that's
all good hopefully this is useful still
to consider the relationship between the
two
so here on the left of these three
images the PDF which is the more
familiar way of representing a
probability distribution we would say
this is a uniform distribution there's a
one in six chance of getting each
outcome from a six-sided die
or in about gaussian bell curve
situation which both of these two middle
and right images show
the PDF of the bell curve is the bell
curve so the PDF is the most familiar
one the uniform distribution is like a
flat line in the PDF the bell curve is
like a bell curve in the PDF
but since you know the maximum and
minimum values
if only asymptotically
then you can make a cumulative
distribution function which starts
basically as low as the function can go
the support for that distribution and it
just accumulates cumulatively
so it's like useful to answer the
question what is the probability of
getting a four or three or two or one
that is two-thirds or what is the
probability of getting a z-score of
below two like two standard deviations
positive what fraction of the curve is
below that z-score on the PDF and that
is addressable by quickly just looking
up a point on this CDF
it turns out that that relationship
between the PDF and the CDF which is
more familiar to again like rolling a
die or evaluating like height in a
classroom
can be used
on the capacity curve discussed earlier
to move to a distribution which when
maximized is in this
spot of Maximum control
so here the CDF from figure 2
gets the derivative and then it becomes
the PDF
with uh this sort of negative
curve shape and that's kind of what was
being hinted at with this Orange Line
being maximized Orange Line being
maximized
is the high point on this
bell curve like but it's not a classical
velcro but it is a mountain it's one
Peak that you can know which side you're
on and therefore pretty easily optimized
towards
um
for analytical convenience we take the
practice from tedorov 2006 of using a
log density the logarithm of a PDF as an
objective function rather than the PDF
itself
the operating point then continues to
appear as local maximum while the gain
determines the cost of movement away
from the operating point and the value
of movement towards it figure 8 shows
the objective function log density
corresponding to the original Barrel
reflex capacity curve
figure 9 further clarifies the
relationship between the various forms
of capacity curve by showing all three
alongside each other so this is a really
nice figure on the top left of the
figure is the figure one with the reflex
that gets dialed up or dialed down to
regulate blood pressure
that's when interpreted as a CDF
can result in a PDF
and that is a single Peak that you can
maximize
instead of trying to calculate a
residual
the shape of this curve becomes slightly
nicer to optimize computationally
when you make it so that it's like a
smoother Bowl
rather than this kind of like inverted
funnel shape
it just
we can go into more detail why I think
that'll be cool why does this log step
matter or does it matter but suffice to
say that this is the big move that lets
you turn the sigmoid
juggling act into
the mountain climb
table one summarizes some key
table one summarizes some key notations
we do not claim our graphical model
accurately captures the anatomy of the
brain it captures reference based
sensory motor control across a hierarchy
of time scales a single feature shared
with a brain
variables
in a table
equations five and six about the
instantaneous capture rate
we'll discuss it in the dot 1.2
section 4.2 also will be nice to discuss
it is optimal foraging Theory suggests a
functional form for allostatic control
do you want to add anything up front
about optimal foraging
no other than I want to I want to talk
with the authors about what does that
even mean
that'll be great all right equation
eight
Global capture rate
section 4.3 feedback or feed forward
control with generative action Concepts
so here's some more formalisms and this
is within not the experimental
psychologist framework
but rather the control theoretic
framework with the allostatic capacity
estimator on the left
section 4.3
equation 10 equation 11.
more variables
stochastic optimal control SOC which was
mentioned earlier
equation 12.
figure 10. this one will be nice to
discuss a hierarchical generative model
capturing multiple time scales and
reference distributions at each level
without addressing empirical questions
about neural hierarchies here we employ
a model with L equal four models to
match figure six
it defines what some of these nodes mean
but the y-axis is increasing time scale
so perhaps slower things higher up and
then on the right is the passage of time
so what does this make you think about
or what is like a way we can approach
the interpretation of this
well I'm not trying to be a smart Apple
but I do find it interesting that L4
gives it gives you quite a bit of
information that that I mean there's
maybe and they they talk about the fact
that there's more than four levels but
they want to focus on those for me I
mean where my brain goes is Okay so
we've got the water we've got the yeast
we got the Hops we got the grains and
that can create quite the
quite the product so you you can go past
that you can add juice or whatever but
you got the four basic ingredients so
now moving through time what does that
enable so again it'd be nice for them to
pull that pull that apart because I
think even in this there's enough there
to
figure a lot of stuff out
right 4.4 feedback control with
generative action Concepts still there
is equation 13 equation 14. and then a
nice quote readers familiar with
predictive processing
and active inference will recognize the
form of the above equation 14.
as a negative free energy or variational
lower Bound for discussion see some
citations since objectives can typically
be written out and interpreted in
several equivalent ways Each of which
can come with its own intuitions there
are Arguments for the computational and
thermodynamic efficiency of minimizing
this specific Divergence in the course
of neural processing but to date the
available evidence does not rule out
other more complex information
divergences for penalizing feedback
correction of movements
so it's pretty interesting how different
lower bounds
variational lower bounds negative free
energies exist like there's expected
free energy and then there's free energy
of the expected future and there's all
of these variants and then each of those
energies can be decomposed differently
like equation 2.6 in the textbook
so it's
interesting to see how first off how did
they converge to this kind of abound
and
from why should it have such resonance
with free energy principle
and what does that mean
and then how can different partitionings
of these energy bounds help us think
about systems that survive
I'll just add here Daniel that uh we're
gonna get to these things but up into
this point in the paper I guess I had a
bit of familiarity and I didn't really
struggle with the sort of the lock step
way that they were going through this
but as soon as we got to equations 13
and the jump to equation 15 and 16.
somebody somebody brighter than me is
going to have to be able to explain that
jump in real simple terms because even
even though I've read it a number of
times I'm still not exactly sure how it
works so again the authors will really
want to bring their their their their
their softest gloves because I need my
handheld
yeah agreed
section 4.4 still here's equation 15.
section 4.4 here's equation 16.
substituting the augmented objective
fancy
J
equation 14.
and the analytical expression for the
optimal feedback controller alone
equation 15 into the Bellman equation
equation 12 would yield
equation 16. let's learn what it is yep
now the intractable recursive term in
the equation is
Etc
finding a way to replace this term will
yield more computationally tractable
problem
the information Divergence term in fancy
J provides just such a way since it can
be written as precisely
the difference between the intractable
hard maximum under Q star star sub Phi
and the more tractable smooth maximum
under the pre-planned action Concept in
symbols equation 17. pretty interesting
okay
um s equation 17 through 21
then the final section section five
discussion
maybe you can help me today so we're 13
through 17 and and then 18 19 and 20 a
way of being able to put together
some of the scale free
formalisms with the scale specific or
scale friendly
um details in particulars when you read
this is that what you saw them trying to
clarify
that's great
question
and so you talk about global
and I think they have to be able to
spell that out and I think yeah but
again I'm I'm
it was all of a sudden things went off
into the ditch for me
here's what I would
um venture
in the early section
there's a contrasting of
homeostasis with allostasis
and about how reward systems are no
longer required under certain
distributed models of brain neuroanatomy
and a function
so I believe that the following
formalisms substitute the augmented
objective
into
in optimality and optimization framework
like the Bellman equation which is often
used for reward maximization so I'm
rewarded by getting to the top of the
mountain
so I'm going to evaluate paths based
upon how much reward they accrue okay
and then curiosity or so on will be
valuable to the extent over the time
Horizon that I considered
it facilitates reward in terms of
elevation
whereas we here are seeing the move
towards that like Optimal
maneuverability maximization
with the pdfcdf relationship
like instead of trying to reduce
Divergence to the midpoint of the CDF
right you maximize your responsiveness
in terms of maximizing the log PDF okay
so I think that's the augmented
um reward function
which is tractable
and then some work remains to
specify that function and how it behaves
perhaps
okay
then section five discussion
interception stabilizes action and
constructs allostatic references
people can look at the quotes anything
to summarize here
no all right 5.1 viewing the brain as an
allostatic optimal controller
the allostatic path integral control
apic model in section 4 implies a number
of specific hypotheses Beyond those
generic to stochastic Optimum control
there's some discussion of shared
modeling choices with active inference
models
perhaps enough for apic to be considered
an active inference model of sorts
and then a few other features that are
shared with active inference models in
strict sense if one even exists
and also related modeling efforts
anything to add
no no they spell that up pretty clearly
here you just want to read through this
right the 5.1 provides some predictions
and some contrasts with the apic model
5.2
the body and the Brain through the lens
of control theory
figure six show how visceral sense data
Ascend in effect to become X afferent
interceptive prediction errors
do you want to explain briefly what an X
affluent means
because people might they do explain
that in the glossary but it's it's
basically an apparent signal on an
operating signal there's a bit of
recursion
there you want to add anything to that
um
I
see the distinction
just to highlight what afferent is
afferent is conducting or conducted
inwards or towards something for the
nerves the central nervous system for
blood vessels the organ supplied right
and um
how would you distinguish exact efforts
just it's just that it's that sort of
cumulative
it's not it's not sort of the the
initial
is what I took away from that the
accumulation of those apparent signals
interesting
I think you're wrong that's what I took
five three interception and capacity
curves
theories of peripheral predictive coding
reason that a neuron's most
metabolically cheap responses should
represent the predictable stimuli
whereas expensive responses are reserved
for the most surprising stimuli
some predictions and suggestions from
Barrett 2017
and findings of dwark in 2013 certain
peripheral interceptors and humans
reduce their operant firing rate to zero
under a constant stimulus
so that's kind of interesting like if no
change
don't tell me about it and that should
be cheap under a model where something
is changing less often than not
um and there's some more uh
hypotheses we have hypothesized that
increases in such responsiveness which
is the imperative in this apic model
could function as rewards positively
reinforcing behavioral trajectories
while decreases in responsiveness could
function as costs negatively reinforcing
behavioral trajectories
so keeping options open over the
infinite time Horizon becomes equivalent
to keeping the business floating or
keeping physiology bounded
yeah
foreign
continuity instead of just maximizing
amount of USD or calories
right but rather having reduced or
bounded surprisal about a range and a
trajectory and a strategy
not in this model as stated here
to generate that
5.3 interception and capacity curves
more
5.4 conclusions finally we return to the
amateur
dodgeball player
the ant mature yeah and
um some summarizations of the apic model
and suggestions about its compatibility
with a referent control hypothesis
and some of its tractability
that's the discussion then appendix B
air conditioning
which we've talked about before but it's
kind of a cool topic so just to skip
through these appendices just discussing
them with the authors we hope then uh
some more equations in equation B
formulating prescription and control
aerodically leads to the free energy
principle fep
more of appendix B appendix C apic model
derivation details
equations
C 0.1.2 full derivation of optimal value
function and transition Dynamics more
equations
the path integral form for the value
desirability function gives its name to
the technique of path integral control
and so on a kind of closing note
we wondered how this connects to the
Bayesian mechanics
and to the path formulation the
rightmost of the three
faces of Bayesian mechanics
and about how coming potentially from
quite a different starting point
and with different
approaches and constraints
some similar features
might have Arisen and been highlighted
in apic
that are also highlighted and relevant
for Bayesian mechanics in the path
formalization and maybe there's like
a kind of unmapped Venn diagram
there and some similarities and
differences
proximity to the last live stream
whether by accident or by intent
makes the
um the way that you look at this paper
um
interesting I'll just say
yeah
agreed well
anything you want to
close with
I think the idea of being able to look
at a mod at modeling and internal
modeling and sort of the coordination of
that either
again kind of as a minimum two other as
a risk management or risk minimizing
exercise therefore a limiting strategy
or as an option generating or an
expanding strategy would be something
really interesting to talk to the
authors about because again I can't I
can't really figure out whether or not
the apic model Works in both domains
until I get past the jump between
formalism 13
and all the way up to 17 18 19 to 20.
but I mean with an explanation of that
and uh and a and a gentle prod it'd be
interesting to find out how
how that works when those things seem to
be be it we as physiological
entities are able to juggle both the
risk management and the options option
generator option expanding so I am
really actually quite excited about that
from a
here's what I'm feeling how should I
read that in terms of what I can how far
out I can make my next bet
from an allostatic perspective I think
that's
really exciting if you if like I said if
I can get
a better sense of how that jump Works in
their model
[Music]
yeah definitely interested in that
infinite time Horizon and that mentality
of like
what's the best physiological
decision over the infinite Horizon
wait that's a great question and yeah
the Eternal now
the presence
and then um also just a little bit more
mundanely like what kind of data
are relevant for this type of model
is it data that already exists for
people
is it something where you can
extrapolate a lot from a sparse data set
or do you need a bunch of replication to
get good statistical confidence on the
model parameter and extract findings
that are like non-trivial
um
and where's this
technology or approach being used or
where could it be used there's like a
lot of things that'll be interesting to
talk about
well
thank you for all the preparation and
help on this one Dean and see you in the
dot one and beyond all right my friend
take care bye